Nicholas and Alexandra is a drama, war, history film
directed by Franklin J. Schaffner.
Tsar Nicholas II, the inept last monarch of Russia, insensitive to the needs of
his people, is overthrown and exiled to Siberia with his family.
Nicholas, played by Michael Jayston.
Alexandra, played by Janet Suzman.
Alexis, played by Roderic Noble.
Olga, played by Ania Marson.
Tatiana, played by Lynne Frederick.
Marie, played by Candace Glendenning.
Nicholas and Alexandra is a 1971 British epic
historical drama film directed by Franklin J.
Schaffner, from a screenplay by James Goldman and Edward Bond based on Robert K.
Massie's 1967 book of the same name.
It tells the story of the last ruling Russian monarch, Tsar Nicholas II of Russia (Michael Jayston),
and his wife, Tsarina Alexandra (Janet Suzman), from 1904 until their deaths in 1918.
The ensemble cast includes Tom Baker as Grigori Rasputin, Laurence Olivier as Sergei Witte, Brian Cox as Leon Trotsky, Ian Holm
as Vasily Yakovlev, Vivian Pickles as Nadezhda Krupskaya, and Irene Worth as The Queen Mother Marie Fedorovna.
The film was theatrically released on 13 December 1971 by Columbia Pictures to mixed
reviews and commercial failure, grossing $7 million on a $9 million budget.
Regardless, the film received six nominations at the 44th Academy Awards, including for Best Picture
and Best Actress (Suzman), and won two: Best Art Direction and Best Costume Design.
The film explores themes of based on novel or book, czar / tsar /
tzar, russian revolution (1917), imperial russia, 1900s.
The tone is emotional.